Hare Krishna
Hare Krishna!
Su Swagatam !
It was a nice and pleasing
experience for me to meet all of you
online, Thank You for registering on this
course on Introduction to Bhagavad Gita
We'll be meeting again and again until I
complete this course-plan and hopefully
this interaction, online interaction will
help us one day to meet in person as well
and I look forward to that pleasant
meeting
But what is our objective?
Our objective is to learn Bhagavad Gita,
isn't it?
Why should you learn Bhagavad Gita?
What is the motivation?
You may say - I am already... You know working as a
teacher, professor, engineer, doctor, nurse
you know, professional,
variegated professionals and you know...
I'm a leader, I'm a housewife,
I'm working professional. You know, I'm a father, I'm a mother, I'm a student
Everybody has something to do
So while we do
everything that we are doing
Is there a role of Bhagavat Gita?
So, that is the first and foremost question you would ask me
and
Let me tell you, Bhagavad Gita
is very important.
In 1988, when I graduated from
Electrical Engineering,
I felt empty within
and I was feeling within a vacuum
and I didn't know what can fill in that
vacuum
and that is the time, I had in my
hand a Bhagavat-Gita.
Let me tell you - Whether you are a student or a
professional, reverses of life are a must!!
As a student, I may be working very hard,
I may be diligent, I may be attending all
the classes but suddenly, I get a fail
grade
isn't it?
So, how do you handle that
situation. I am doing very well in my
business and suddenly, I make a huge loss.
How do I handle it?
or I am a young boy
and getting married to young girl. You
know, everything is so nice but within months,
our natural match is not there, we
start quarreling and suddenly we go to
the court for divorce.
So, these are the
reverses of life that, you and me all of
us, we are going to face. It doesn't
matter, whether I'm in the nascent state of
my career or I'm very mature in my
career, doesn't matter, reverses of life
is the ultimate truth of this world
and Bhagavad Gita teaches us how to deal
with these reverses. This is the only
science that is called Life Science.
Anything that happens to me, how do I
deal with that. If you have a disease,
you can go to a doctor, isn't it but
when you have a disease
like reverses of life
No doctor can cure it.
Reverses in life
My near and dear ones,
They met an accident and
My whole world collapses, under my feet.
How do I deal with it?
So here no medicine would work
No engineering would work,
None of my wealth can help me.
I need
A Life Science.
Okay
And that is why
We must read Bhagavad Gita.
I've given you a little hint, why we must study
Bhagavad Gita. Okay and in particular you
must know that, Bhagavad Gita is the
quintessence of all the Vedic knowledge
that are there in the form of Vedas, in
the form of Upanishads, Aryankas , Samhitas, Puranas.
You name anything. Okay, this is
the quintessence. This is the
gist of everything that is there and
How many verses are there in Bhagavat Gita?
Only 700 verses
That means in this world of
busy life, we have an opportunity, just to
bath ourselves in 700 verses of
Bhagavad Gita and get
The lessons of Life
Is that, not very wonderful.
I think
you will appreciate. So, I welcome you
again, to join this course for
registering. After you get benefit , I
would request you, please tell your near
and dear ones, your friends, colleagues
let everybody come and join us and learn
the science of Bhagavad  Gita.
This Bhagavad Gita that we are
going to discuss, this a timeless science.
Every science, every knowledge, a society
possesses, at any point of time, evolves with time
But Bhagavad Gita doesn't
evolve
Why?
Because it's the science of the
Soul.
Soul or Atma is eternal and science
of the soul, has to be beyond the
influence of time and this is
Bhagavad Gita
it's the science of life.
In fact, in Bhagavad Gita the entirety of
existence, the way it exists, the complete
science of its existence
is there
That
means,  if I know Bhagavad Gita, I have an
opportunity, to know everything in
totality, not in a fragmented way
Okay.
So, let me tell you
everything is existing, before you are
born, (before) I was born.
Before this universe (was) created,
The Eternal World is existing.
Temporary
world, they manifest
they unmanifest but the source of this
temporary world is always existing
and hence
Once you know, how to acquire
knowledge from Bhagavad Gita
It's fully satisfying
You don't need any other
literature
Okay.
So, this Bhagavad Gita
has been translated all over the world. In
particularly,
International Society of Krishna consciousness founded by
has taken a lead in translating Bhagavad Gita into all major
languages of this world. So, you can have your copy as well in your own
language. If you have any doubt, please
join us in our Youtube channel as well
as Facebook page
and you will see
that
we will help you to get a copy of Bhagavad Gita
The Bhagavad Gita, that we will be
following.
So, this is a eternal science.
There are two things:
One is Divinity,  the
other is mundane.
In mundane, you see all
inabilities, imperfections. In Divinity
there is only perfection.
In mundane, there
is always incompleteness,
In Divinity - there is completeness.
So,
This is what is Bhagavad Gita.
Bhagavad Gita takes us from the
plane of imperfection to the plane of
perfection.
This is a very nice
analogy. I'm giving you a very nice
analogy.
Suppose, you are residing near
a big reservoir, imagine a huge lake
or a ever flowing river then, you will
never look for a pond or a well, anything
because
All that water is necessary for
your cooking, for agriculture
everything you can get from this big
reservoir.
Similarly,  Bhagavad Gita is that book
that contains all the knowledge that you
need to live a perfect life. As a human
being, we want perfection. We do not want
to lead a life like animal without any
purpose. In human life, we need a purpose
and this purpose of life, as it is given
to us in Bhagavad Gita. So, the science of
life - as it is, is not there. In
Bhagavad Gita,
when it started 5000 years ago
Krishna spoke to Arjuna
All of you know
this, Right?
Krishna spoke (to) Arjuna - the Bhagavad Gita
What is meaning of the
Bhagavad Gita?
Bhagavan and Bhagavad .
That which comes from Bhagavan, is Bhagavad.
and Gita means song
The song of the Lord.
When God speaks, something amazing
happens.
Imagine, in your locality, if there is an
announcement that a very big man is
coming.
Imagine, a Nobel laureate or president of
America, Prime Minister of India, they're
coming. So, there will be huge gathering
Right?
But instead, if someone says God
has come to speak
What will happen?
Everyone, from every walk of life doesn't
matter, you are in university, you are a
businessman,
you are an administrator, you are in service
provider category,  all walks of life,
irrespective of caste, creed, religion,
everybody will come and hear. And this is
exactly is Bhagavad Gita.
As I told you in the beginning, this is the
motivation!
Why should we study Bhagavad Gita ?,
The reverses of life.
Nobody, in this world is freed from
reverses of life. Just like Arjuna was
confused in the battlefield of
Kuruksetra. Similarly, we are all confused
in our own battlefield. As a student in
the field of study, we are confused. As
businessman, in the field of business we
are confused. As an administrator, in the field
of administration we are confused.
Everyone is confused here or there and
Bhagavad Gita, is there to remove that confusion.
You know sometime
we like to do something, if that
something has been done by some great
personality.
isn't it?
You know when I was
growing up in my childhood days, you know,
I used to read a regular
monthly journal(magazine) and that
magazine, you know every time, there will
be a corner where the favourite food of
great personalities
and when I used to
read that I will go and tell my mom. Mumma,
please make this item.
Right!
So this is what!
we have a tendency to follow, you
know, people who are in higher set up.
In Bhagavad Gita also it is said:
Isn't it?
That whatever, the great people,
they do
the normal ordinary people they follow.
So now, let us hear from some
great people
What they say?
Here is
Mahatma Gandhi
The Father of the Nation
And this is happening to me, for last
30-35 years, I'm studying Bhagavad Gita
and every time I read a verse
I have a
new experience
and this will happen to you
Albert Einstein
All of you know, right?
One of the greatest scientists, we
have seen on this earthly planet.
He says
This is Albert Einstein
Aldous Huxley
one of my favorite
philosophers
Before, I took interest in Bhagavad Gita, I was very philosophical
and I have read
not only Aldous Huxley,
Spinoza, Erasmus
Then we have, our Jiddu Krishnamurti
many-many philosophers - I have read the books
and what Aldous Huxley saying
and then
There is another person, you know
you might have
studied his book
He's a Nobel
laureate, one of his books is "Siddharth".
In fact, to write this book he came to
India, he learned the Indian culture and
then he wrote this book Siddhartha. What
he says?
so Hermann Hesse, the German Nobel laurette, he says
and
Before, we enact our journey, journey to be bathing in the message of Bhagavad Gita
It is
important, that we understand the principle
or spirit behind learning
Bhagavad Gita. Any knowledge that you
want to have, you must approach
that knowledge with utmost humility.
When you go to our school, colleges we
must have respect for our teachers. And
Bhagavad Gita is about spiritual
knowledge, knowledge perfect, knowledge
eternal and hence our attitude, our
approach to this knowledge has to be
that of utmost humility. In Bhagavad Gita,
Krishna says Himself:
Three points are told here,
Tad viddhi pranipatena
So, we must follow
proper etiquette.
A civilization is known
by the standard of conduct or etiquette
the civilization follows.
So 'Tad viddhi' -
What is that etiquette?
Etiquette is
Pranipatena,
With respect and reverence
we should approach - a teacher.
and we should not simply come in front
of the teacher. Suppose, you go to a
teacher and you have no question, you
will not learn anything from him.
So pariprashnena,
that means I must
learn how to ask submissive inquiry
If I do not have questions within my mind.
Like everybody asks questions about
You know
if you are hungry, then you are
asking question -
where can I get food?
If you're thirsty you are asking -
Where can
I get water?
but such questions even
animals ask.
As a human being, we must
learn to ask questions like
what is the purpose of this creation?
Why the solar system is organized the way it is?
Why there are variegated
species of life?
Why I go through suffering?
Although I do not work for it.
So many questions, you can have unlimited
questions.
Unless you have such questions
Unless you have a question like -
Who am I?
I don't want to die but I'm dying, who am I?
When I ask such questions
then I must approach a spiritual master.
And there pariprashnena, I must ask
submissive questions and then
Sevaya
I must have the proper etiquette, to render
service to such a wonderful personality.
Why he is a wonderful personality?
Tattva-Darshi
Tattva Darsinah
plural
Tattva Darshi
singular.
So Tattva Darsinah
So, these spiritual masters, they have
seen the truth and hence, they can make
me to understand the truth.
So this is a very wonderful and
auspicious beginning we are making and
I'm pretty hopeful, that all of us
together will have a very very divine
and pleasurable journey
that will reveal
the Self within.
Hare Krishna!
Thank you very much.